So today's דף daf *daf* is ע"א *Ayin Aleph*, we pick up
with the top of ע"א *Ayin Aleph*, the משנה mishna, *Mishna*, continuing
to discuss what happens when somebody sells a field. And this משנה
mishna, *Mishna* will sound familiar because it's been quoted before. So you
don't sell certain types of things that are in the field, you
also don't sell these like sycamore trees or carob trees which are
considered to be like an independent field. And here comes what I
would consider to be a bit of a חידוש chiddush, *chiddush*, was
a חידוש chiddush? *chiddush* when we said something similar by a house
but even more so by a field. ולא את הבור *Velo et
habor*, you also don't ולא את הגת *Velo et hagat*. You don't
sell the wells in the field, like I mean you know imagine
that buying a whole wheat field and not getting the wells which
are I presume a necessary part of the irrigation. And you don't
sell the what do you call it
the press the oil press ולא את
השובך *Velo et hashovach* and not the pigeon coop. What?
What? בין חרבין בין ישובין *Bein charevin bein yushuvin*, whether they are
in you know not in operation, empty, desolate, or whether they're in
operation.
So I mean to me the בור bor *bor* is the most
interesting of that. Of course the other question is is that like
the case of the carob tree and the what do you call
it tree which is even if you said כל מה שבתוכה kol
mah shebetokhah, *Kol mah shebetochah* sycamore even if you said כל מה
שבתוכה kol mah shebetokhah *Kol mah shebetochah* you don't sell that right?
Or is that only in the what do you call it is
that only if you don't say כל מה שבתוכה kol ma shebesocha,
*Kol mah shebetochah*? So that's also not clear.
Okay. וצריך ליקח לו דרך *Vetzarich likach lo derech*. Now this is
something that we've seen before. While you retain ownership to the well
or to these other things, you might still own those but you
don't have access rights to them. So each party loses out. The
guy doesn't get his well, you get the well but you don't
get access to it. דברי רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Divrei Rabbi Akiva*.
That's what Rabbi Akiva says who says that מוכר בעין יפה be'ayin
yafa מוכר *mocher be'ayin yaffah mocher*. So it's not so much בעין
יפה be'ayin yafa *be'ayin yaffah* that you give him the well, but
it is בעין יפה be'ayin yafa *be'ayin yaffah* that you don't hold
back for yourself also the path through his field. The well is
a different thing, they said that wasn't sold. But what I did
sell, I sold him fully. So I don't have access through his
field to get to my well. That's what Rabbi Akiva says. וחכמים
אומרים אינו צריך *Vachachamim omrim einu tzarich*. Nope. You the same way
you withheld the well, you withheld the path to the well. And
you don't have to get special access to the well. You don't
like own the ground like a specific path, but you have access
rights to the well. ומודה רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, בזמן שאמר לו
חוץ מאלו *Umodeh Rabbi Akiva bizman she'amar lo chutz me'eilu*, Rabbi Akiva
admits or concedes that if you said I am selling you everything
except for the well, since you didn't have to say except for
the well, if you do say it, so in that case חוץ
מאלו *chutz me'eilu* שאינו צריך ליקח לו דרך *she'einu tzarich likach lo
derech*. That extra language was said explicitly in order to indicate that
not only did you have the well which you would have had
by default, but you have access to the well as well. Okay
now. מכרן לאחר *Macharan le'acher*. Now let's see what was the flip.
You held on to the field and you sold the well to
someone. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר אינו צריך ליקח לו דרך
*Rabbi Akiva omer einu tzarich likach lo derech*. The person who has
the well does not have to get access rights because again this
is בעין יפה b'ayin yafeh, הוא מוכר *be'ayin yaffah hu mocher*. And
you have to say it both ways because you might have thought
that you know the חכמים's Chachamim. *Chachamim's* position wasn't a עין יפה
ayin yafe, עין רעה *ayin yaffah ayin raah* position. It was a
position that with the well always comes access rights. So if you
keep the well you have access rights and if you sell the
well you give the guy the access rights. And now we're finding
out it's not that way. It's not that it's bundled together. It's
that Rabbi Akiva says always essentially favors the buyer and the חכמים
Chachamim *Chachamim* always favor the seller. So when you so when you
sell the well to somebody Rabbi Akiva says oh well then that
guy the buyer you're בעין יפה מוכר *be'ayin yaffah mocher*. The buyer
gets the well with the access rights. So he says אינו צריך
ליקח לו דרך *einu tzarich likach lo derech* in that case he
has the access rights. וחכמים אומרים צריך ליקח לו דרך *Vachachamim omrim
tzarich likach lo derech*. No the חכמים Chachamim. *Chachamim* favor the seller.
So you sold him the well but he doesn't have the access
rights and if he wants it he has to buy it from
you. All right to all of that we've seen before and we
are not going to revisit that now. במה דברים אמורים במוכר *Bameh
devarim amurim bemocher*. When is this true that you might sort of
sell the well and not sell the access rights? That's if you
are selling. So then we could sort of say like בעין רעה
הוא מוכר *be'ayin raah hu mocher* according to the חכמים *Chachamim*. You're
keeping more to yourself. אבל בנותן מתנה matana. *Aval benoten matanah* if
you give a gift okay in that case נותן את כולה *noten
et kullah* you give it fully. So not only do you give
the well according to the חכמים *Chachamim* you also give the access
rights. Now that's according to the חכמים *Chachamim* of בעין רעה *be'ayin
raah* and that's about this issue of access rights. But how far
how broad does this במה דברים אמורים *bameh devarim amurim* go? So
if you take a look at the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* okay I
mean not the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* at the רשב"ם Rashbam... *Rashbam*, the
second wide line the רשב"ם Rashbam. *Rashbam* says the following. אבל בנותן
מתנה matana. נותן את כולה *Aval benoten matanah noten et kullah* he
says כל הני דאמרו לא מכר Kol hani deamru lo makhar, *kol
hani de'amru lo machar* all the things we said in the previous
משנה mishna, *Mishna* so.
That you know you did not sell with it. Remember, what did
we say in the previous משנה mishna you didn't sell with it?
What did we have there? We had the stones that were not
necessary for it, the wood that was not necessary for it. We
also of course had a guard hut, we had the sycamore and
the carob tree. Okay, now it's not for it. Now, all we
had all these things you didn't sell. כל הני דאמרו לא מכר,
mecher and even ואפילו הני דאינם בכלל מטיא בתוכה, vafillu hani deaynam
bikhlal matia betokhah, even the things that is the least part of
it, that even when you say everything in it you don't include.
What are the things that are not included when you say I'm
selling you the field and everything in it? כגון חרוב המורכב וסדן
השקמה, Kegon kharuv hamurkav vesadan hashikmah, like these carob and sycamore trees,
ובור וגת ושובך. ubor vegath veshovakh. Now, by the way, parenthetically, not
parenthetically, the רשב״ם Rashbam is telling us that our משנה, Mishna which
was not clear in our משנה, Mishna. of the things that are
not sold, right, the well and whatever and, you know, the pigeon
coop etc., the רשב״ם Rashbam is saying that those are so much
separate that even if you say everything in it, they're not included.
Right, so you have these three categories: things that סתם stam are
not included, things that are included when you say everything in it,
like certain types of, you know, of sticks and of stones, of
harvested wheat. You know, a lot of stuff, it's in it, it's
in it, you said everything with it. And then there are things
that even when you say everything in it are seen as a
separate type of a field and are not included. Okay, the sycamore,
the carob, the well—I mean, the well for God's sake, I mean
that's surprising—okay, the pigeon coop, all those things. Even that third category
that is not included when you say everything in it is included
when you're נותן מתנה. notayn matana. He says, והכי מוכח גבי הקדש
וכו׳ vehakhi mukhach gabei hekdesh etc. והוא הדין לכל הנך. vehu hadin
lekhol hanakh. וטעמא משום דנותן בעין יפה נותן יותר מדי, Vetaama mishum
denotayn beyayin yafa notayn yotayr midai,
excessively generous. ואפילו מאי דלא הוה בכלל שדה הוא הקבוע בתוכה שדה,
Vafillu mai delo havah bikhlal sadeh hu hakavua betokhah sadeh, even though
it's not considered part of the field or even in the field
in a certain way, in another way it really is in the
field. I mean, we exerted a lot of effort to say that
the carob and the sycamore tree are conceptually a different field, but
basically they really are in the field and therefore they're included when
you give it as a מתנה. matana Okay, then the רשב״ם Rashbam
has an interesting little הערה. hearah. He says, but those are at
least things that are connected conceptually. ומיהו אם יש מעות בשדה או
תבואה תלושה שאינה צריכה לקרקע כל כך, Umihu im yesh maot basadeh
o tvua tlusha sheayna tzerikha lekarka kol kakh, let's say there's something
in the field that's just being like happens temporarily to be in
the field but is in no conceptual way connected. You dropped your
wallet in the field, okay, or there's cut grain that is not
using the field itself, it just happens to be being stored there
for the moment but it's not in any way connected. In that
case, או כל דבר שלא הוצרך לתנא דמתניתין להזכיר, o kol davar
shelo hutzrakh letanna demasnitin lehazkir, anything that was so obviously not connected
it wasn't in our משנה, Mishna ולא ממו לא מכר משום דמילתא
דפשיטא הוא, velo mamo lo makhar mishum demilsa depshita hu, that he
says that would not go even in a case of מתנה. matana.
Okay, but מתנה matana is pretty broad the way the רשב״ם Rashbam
reads this, not just access to the field like a right of
access, but actual physical objects are sold with it and not just
stuff in the second category, not just stuff that are included when
I say כל מה שבתוכה, kol ma shebesocha. even things that are
not included when I say כל מה שבתוכה kol ma shebesocha. are
considered to be packaged together in the case of a מתנה. matana,
Okay, so that's a very new broad category, inclusive category.
Now the משנה Mishna goes on. האחין שחלקו, Haachin shechileku, if
brothers divided a field, each owned by, you know, it was owned
by the father, father died, they divided the field, so זכו בשדה
זכו בכולה. zakhu basadeh zakhu bekulah. So when they get the field,
they get all of it. Now what that means is the way
the רשב״ם Rashbam explains it—I just have to scroll erase this beautiful
little chart
here—anyway, explains is is that you might remember like there was a
debate before which is brothers owned this field and there's a well
here, right, and you split it, so there's a question, you know,
ראובן Reuven and there was a whole point that ראובן Reuven could
say like I still get access to that half because, you know,
this is the way it was when our father was alive, that
that well was used for the whole field, right, so I therefore
should, you know, continue to get access. So that might be, it
might be that he continues to have access to it. That was
discussed debated before. But that's not our question. Our question isn't if
you have access. The question is, since normally when you sell a
field you don't sell the well, maybe you should say, okay, all
we did here was we split the field when we agreed to
split it, but that well is still jointly owned by both of
us. Right, that's a different question about questions about access. It's a
question about have we actually, you
know, who owns it, who can have access to?
Well, we don't know, maybe you do have access. We're not discussing
access right now. We're discussing that if I sold שמעון Shimon the
field, okay, it would not have included the well, alright, because that's
מכר שדה לא מכר. makhar sadeh lo makhar. However, if I split
it with שמעון, Shimon, if these are brothers who split it, does
שמעון—and Shimon there the point is yes, שמעון Shimon gets full ownership
of the well because the whole idea of splitting an inheritance is
that you like completely split, you know, you split, like you take
your half, I take my half, we go our separate ways, like
אברהם Avraham and
לוט. Lot. So therefore, even though when there's a sale, you might
maintain like this משנה just said, you got your chicken coop here,
you got other stuff, etc. That's if you're selling. But if you're
splitting an inheritance, the whole idea is you take that half, you
leave me alone, I'm taking this half, I leave you alone, and
therefore we assume everything in the field goes with it. Yes.
That's counterintuitive though. I mean, when I'm doing a sale with a
stranger, I would expect after the sale we're done with each other.
Right.
Whereas if it's a brother, right, you stay connected.
Yeah, I hear the point. I hear the point. On the other
hand, like maybe the other... I guess the point is that on
one hand, I think the thinking is that in the case of
a sale, it's like a business deal, so like I'm, you know,
I'm sort of very much thinking in terms of like dollars and
cents and I, you know, what do I still own and what
do I not own? Whereas here it's more like, you know, we
want to break, you know, we don't want to be held together
by the estate anymore. We're independent entities. But I hear your point,
you know, it's family, so more the reason you could say. Let's
take a look. That's what the רשב"ם... Rashbam I'm just looking at
the line in the רשב"ם. Rashbam He says: זכה בכולה אפילו בור
וגב ושוובך שבשדה קנה כיון שזה נטל שדה אחת וזה אחת כנגדו
הסתלק זה משל זה נסתקן
לו. zacha bechula afilu bor vegav veshovach shebasade kana keivan sheze natul
sade achas veze achas kenegdo histalek ze mishel ze nistaken lo. Right?
The whole point is that they should be able to be like,
you know, break off. As he says, but if there's a question
of like access, the well example wasn't so good because they totally
broke it. ראובן Reuven doesn't need access to the well, he doesn't
own the well. But let's say, I don't know, this is the
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, right, and שמעון Shimon now needs to get
access through ראובן Reuven to get to the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim.
So could be that there שמעון Shimon maintains a right of access
that's based on the other argument: Hey look, when our father was
alive, you know, wherever you were in the field you were able
to get to the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, I'm not giving that
right up. Okay, so that might be like an access right. But
the idea that the point of splitting an estate is to let
each one go their separate ways, that's at least the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam explains it.
They could have...
yeah, they could, but they chose not to.
They could have split it so half the well.
Yeah, but you could also imagine a case where like the well
is here and the שובך shovach is here and all like... so
you know there's no good way to split it, you know, some...
it's gonna fall into one person's estate. Okay, you would hope that
when they decide to split it they include the value of these
things, so where they draw the line, the line doesn't have to
be exactly down the middle, you know.
Alright. Now, המחזיק בנכסי הגר,
hamachzik benichsei
hager,
back to this גר ger who dies and the property is הפקר.
hefker. So החזיק בשדה החזיק בכולה. hechzik basade hechzik bechula. If you
take possession of the field, you take possession of all of it,
and this is all of the things in the field, which is
also ironic, because here we've been saying that this sycamore or this
carob tree or whatever are so important, right, that when you sell
the field and even you say כל מה שבתוכה, kol ma shebesocha,
you don't get that tree. Okay, and you don't get this well
or whatever. Those are independent things even if you say כל מה
שבתוכה. ma shebetocha. Comes along נכסי הגר nichsei hager and a guy
does a little חזקה chazaka act, he's digging with a shovel, okay,
he does a little חזקה chazaka act over here and he gets
the whole field including these things, even though those things are not
included when you say כל מה שבתוכה. So what's the logic for
it? So the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it is you might
remember that we discussed if you have a נכסי הגר nichsei hager
and it has a boundary line and you do a חזקה chazaka
on one part of it, yeah that's the guy with the shovel
again, it does not work on the other part, right? Because the
boundary line conceptually says they're separate fields and therefore if it's הפקר,
hefker, right, if I'm selling I can sell two separate fields with
one act of חזקה, chazaka, but if it's נכסי הגר nichsei hager
they're considered separate and a חזקה chazaka on this doesn't work on
this. So why is this different? We said these are like conceptually
like different fields, different objects. So the רשב"ם Rashbam has a good
חאפ. chap. The רשב"ם Rashbam says, okay, but let's say you had
two fields here without a boundary line, then even though they were
conceptually two fields, okay, let's say I don't know this was wheat
and this was barley or something, or just
somehow they were conceptualized as two separate fields, without a physical boundary
line it would work on both. So that's what he wants to
say we're talking about here. These are two separate fields, so if
you sell this you don't sell this, you don't sell this, but
there's no physical boundary line and therefore a חזקה chazaka on this
works on everything. So he's trying to like, you know, walk this
narrow line between them. They're not enough distinct that when you sell
the field you don't sell them, even when you say כל מה
שבתוכה, but they're enough connected that if you give a מתנה matana.
they're included in it, and if you do a חזקה chazaka with
part of the field for נכסי הגר. nichsei hager. it works for
everything. Alright, that's that, and the last line is המקדיש את
השדה הקדיש את כולה. hamakdish es hasadeh hikdish es kula. The same
way by a מתנה, matana if I give this field, it includes
all of this. If I מקדיש makdish it, then I'm also assumed
that I'm going to be very generous, I'm giving something to הקדש,
hekdesh, so it includes these things as well. Let me just finish
the line. רב שמעון אומר Rav Shimon omer no, המקדיש את השדה
לא הקדיש אלא חרוב המורכב וסדן השקמה. hamakdish es hasadeh lo hikdish
ela charuv hamurkav vesadan hashikma. The only things that would go would
be these trees, but would not be included your, you know, your
well or your pigeon coop or whatever, those would not be included,
only this. So that's an interesting position. It seems like he does
not disagree by מתנה. matana. By מתנה matana? he says everything would
go. By הקדש hekdesh you're not as generous, so everything doesn't go.
So if this doesn't go and this doesn't go, the question is
why does this go? What's that makes the trees different? So we'll
have to see about that in the גמרא. Gemara Yeah.
Wait, he had another tree, you still give.
Not the but not other things.
So he they can walk to it if I don't know.
But anyway he doesn't treat the point is he fundamentally doesn't treat
הקדש hekdesh like מתנה. matana He says הקדש hekdesh is a narrower
gift, it's only the field itself, okay, but for some reason the
trees get thrown in and we'll have to see about that in
the גמרא. Gemara. Yeah.
So go down to the נכסי הגר nichsei hager field, the מצרא,
metza, to draw a tree in there.
Okay. Or yeah oh right.
So same tree, same tree. Right.
No, this is a חרוב charuv and this is a שקמה.
shikma.
So without the מצרא metza you don't treat the entire the both
those two fields as one. Yes. What about the tree?
Yes, that's the whole point of the משנה. Yeah, yeah. So the
רשב"ם's Rashbam question is why are you מחזיק machzik the tree if
it's a separate field conceptually? And his answer is it's a separate
field without a מצרא. metza. Right, for the for the נכסי הגר.
nichsei hager. Yeah.
Did they have property taxes in these days? What? Did they have
property taxes?
Yeah, to the government, sure. The גמרא Gemara talks about that, yeah.
We did a whole thing about דינא דמלכותא dina dimalchuta and about
ta- yeah, we did.
It was a business this thing of like, you know, going around
finding fields every now and then.
Oh you mean that people didn't pay. Yeah, you'd have to pay
the government the property tax. We dealt with that, yeah. Michael.
No, so I'm serious, like when you מקדיש makdish something, is he
saying that you were not מקדיש makdish you did not retain a
right of access to these trees if you מקדיש makdish the rest
of the field?
Well רב שמעון Rav Shimon says you also were מקדיש makdish the
tree. You mean you don't retain the right of access to these?
Yeah, that would presumably be correct. Yeah.
Right. So so you have technically not if you're really you're more
הקדש hekdesh for walking through the field, right?
Yeah, and that also we'll see that has to do with why
you also sell the tree. Okay, let's let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara מאי שנא מכר ומאי שנא מתנה. mai shna mecher
u'mai shna matana. What is the difference between מכר mecher and מתנה?
matana Now, the obvious difference is בעין יפה or not.
But with the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it is okay, I
get בעין יפה that maybe it would have included, I don't know,
some like access or something, like access to your you know you
would have given the guy the well with the access. But how
is it so generous is the question that it includes all these
things that okay that are not even considered like מה שבתוכה. So
again the גמרא Gemara could have just answered בעין יפה but let's
see what the גמרא Gemara answers. So
פירש יהודה בן נקוסא
לפני רבי. peireish Yehuda bin Nakusa lifnei Rebbi. So יהודה בן נקוסא
Yehuda bin Nakusa explained in front of רבי. Rebbi. זה פירש וזה
לא פירש. zeh peireish vezeh lo peireish. This explained and this didn't
explain. And of course the word he explained was with the words
פירש. peireish. זה פירש וזה לא פירש. zeh peireish vezeh lo peireish.
This guy explicated and this guy didn't explicate. So somehow it makes
it sound like, not clear what he's saying, it's not a very
helpful explanation. Okay. Sounds like he's saying that one of these in
the case of the מכר mecher you were ex- I don't know,
in the מתנה matana you were explicit you gave everything and in
the מכר mecher you weren't explicit but like what do you mean?
Nothing is explicit. So the גמרא Gemara says
הי זה פירש וזה לא פירש? hai zeh peireish vezeh lo peireish?
What do you mean in one case he ex- he explicated and
one case he didn't? זה לא פירש וזה לא פירש. zeh lo
peireish vezeh lo peireish. Both in the case of מכר mecher, and
מתנה matana... you did not explicate whether you were selling the other
stuff or not. You haven't answered the question. Why do we assume
מתנה matana, is so much more inclusive? אלא זה היה לו לפרש
וזה לא היה לו לפרש. ela zeh haya lo lefareish vezeh lo
haya lo lefareish. One should have explicated, one should have not. Now
what does that mean? So the way רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom and
רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel explain it, it means if you are the
buyer
and you wanted to clarify wait wait wait, you're selling me the
field, does that include the well? Does that include the tree? Does
that include this? You're paying good money, so you feel totally comfortable
and you should be asking those questions and getting the seller to
explicate and to say to you if you wanted to get the
well you should have said wait, I want to make it clear
this includes the well, I need you to write the well in
that שטר. shtar. Okay, so you were sort of היה לו לפרש
haya lo lefareish meaning you the buyer
on you. force explication of those issues, and since you didn't, they're
not included. But if you're the guy receiving the gift, so here
I am, I'm going to say to Jenner, Jenner, I like you
so much, happy anniversary, I understand you've recent anniversary, was it your
birthday or something I thought I saw something on Facebook? Anniversary? No?
Okay fine. Anyway, okay. So that'll be a מתנה... matana, oh, I
thought it was... okay anyway, I'm going to give you my field.
Just wait a second here, Dove, does that include the trees or
not? Does that include the well or not? Like you don't say
that when you're receiving a gift, right? So the irony is since
she would have been considered like ungrateful as a receiver of a
gift to say, wait, I need you to be clear whether I'm
getting the trees or not, she's not in a position to say
that. So since she's not in a position to say that, therefore
we assume that the fact that it wasn't said doesn't mean it
wasn't given, and we're actually going to assume that like it was
given. So that's a very interesting like dynamic, right? I mean it
would seem that it's basically first based on the idea that you
would not... it seems like it's also, I mean it can't be...
I don't think you can say something like that without also saying
that הנותן מתנה בעין יפה נותן. hanoten matana b'ayin yafa noten. Okay,
but together with the עין יפה נותן ayin yafa noten is the
fact that there was no expectation that she was in a position
to ask me to be more explicit. And since she wasn't in
a position to ask me to be more explicit, right, the absence
of saying that does not mean that they're not included. So combined
with... I think you have to combine it with בעין יפה נותן.
b'ayin yafa noten. Okay, as opposed to a sale, a, there's an
assumption that I only give stuff that I get paid for and
I don't... you know, we assume that I'm not being generous. You
know, even רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva generosity, remember, did not include a
tree and a well or whatever. His generosity included like access to
the well. So there it's all about you get what you pay
for. And since you get what you pay for, whatever, everybody is
being very מקפיד makpid not to give more than they're giving. There's
a presumption, right, that you're not giving anything that you said you
didn't give, and the other person should have explicated, okay? But here
there's not necessarily those presumptions. So that seems to be the answer.
All right, so let's take a look. There's other ways of explaining
it, but I think that's the best. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara,
says like this. ההוא דאמר להו, hahu d'amar lehu, somebody said to
some people... ההוא דאמר להו, hahu d'amar lehu, somebody was dying presumably
said to his heirs,
ביתא דמחזיק מאה גרבי, beita d'machzik mea garvei, give to so-and-so my
house that contains... that is big enough that it is the area
that it can contain a hundred barrels of wine,
a hundred barrels, whatever thereof.
אשתכח דהוי מחזיק מאה ועשרין. ishtakach d'havi machzik mea v'esrin. They went
to the one house they knew this guy owned and they found
that it was rather than being 10 by 10, right, let's
say... let's imagine that a square אמה ama contains a barrel of
wine. So rather than being 10 by 10 אמות, amot, it was
10 by 12. It could contain 120, the
footprint, 120 barrels of wine. So he obviously wasn't referring to this
house. So maybe what? So maybe... well
that's what I was going to say. יש בכלל מאה. yesh bichlal
mea. It does contain 100 barrels. It contains 120 barrels. But anyway,
but maybe he only gave five-sixths of the house to this guy.
How should we interpret what he said? Okay, so this is a
type of a נותן מתנה, noten matana, presumably this sounds like it's
a case of a guy on his deathbed. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, because anybody who is saying, right, and not
giving, normally the idea that your words are binding in themselves is
a context of giving on your deathbed. So it says, let's take
a look...
okay, so where are we? Okay, so... אמר מר זוטרא, amar Mar
Zutra, מאה אמר ליה מאה ועשרין לא אמר ליה. mea amar leh
mea v'esrin lo amar leh. He said a hundred, not 120. And
therefore what? Either he didn't give anything or he only gave five-sixths.
So אמר ליה... amar leh... so אמר ליה. amar leh. רב אשי
Rav Ashi אמר, amar, מי לא תנן במדאמרן במכר אבל בנותן מתנה
נותן את כולן. mi lo tnan bim'deamran bimchar aval b'noten matana noten
et kulan. So our משנה says that when you give a gift
you give everything. So everything contained within... now you could have said,
you know, everything contained within is different
than... you don't necessarily... these aren't all the exact same application. It's
one thing to say a field means I'll interpret it as everything
in the field. As opposed to here, I'm trying to identify which
house did he give, this house or a different house? Or not
no house at all since he doesn't have this object, he didn't
give anything. Or maybe if he said a hundred, he was being
very clear. He meant I'm giving you this amount of the house
and not the full house. So just because you say in our
משנה you get everything doesn't mean here we should interpret it to
mean the whole house. But רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying, yes,
that's what we should do, we should always read these things in
the more generous way.
מי לא תנן במדאמרן במכר אבל בנותן מתנה נותן את כולן? mi
lo tnan bim'deamran bimchar aval b'noten matana noten et kulan? אלמא מאן
דיהיב מתנה בעין יפה יהיב הכא נמי מאן דיהיב מתנה בעין יפה
יהיב. alma man deyahiv matana b'ayin yafa yahiv hacha nami man deyahiv
matana b'ayin yafa yahiv. So here too it was with a generous
eye. Obviously if he had said I'm giving him five-sixths of my
house we would have said five-sixths and not the whole thing. But
here if it's a question of interpretation we'll say he means he
was rounding, he was saying it contains at least a hundred barrels,
or whatever we'll interpreted in a more generous way. So this now
becomes a sort of a broader principle. By the way, notice also,
right, that this is like, you know, it doesn't seem to fit
into the issue before of חייה לו לפיה. chaya lo lefiha. I
guess you could say the same thing, like the other side wasn't
going to ask for clarification. Okay, but it becomes, you combine these
things to sort of read this, as they will read these in
very generous terms. That being said, I want to point out it's
not discussed here but it's discussed elsewhere, but it's healthy, healthy or
helpful to point out that this is, there's a counterbalance of principle
here, which is
the principle of דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebelev einam devarim. The
גמרא, Gemara. which is, it does not apply as much by a
giving of somebody who gives a gift. There's some classic גמרות Gemarot
that say that somebody heard that, I don't know, his son died
and he, and he said, "או גוואלד, oy gevalt, you know, whatever,
my son died, I'm giving all of my property to somebody else."
Okay, the guy was old, he was on his deathbed, whatever, and
then it turns out that his son was alive. So he said,
"Ah, well, had he realized that his son was actually alive, he
never would have said such a thing." The whole sale is בטל.
batel. Okay, the whole gift is בטל. batel. Other such situations where
somebody gives a gift because they have certain assumptions, it turns out
the assumptions were false, and we say the whole sale was בטל.
batel. And the question that everybody asks is whatever happened to דברים
שבלב אינם דברים? devarim shebelev einam devarim? So some ראשונים Rishonim try
to answer it and say, well, this is something that was בלב
כל אדם. belev kol adam. It wasn't just something that his, in
his head, it was obvious to everybody, these were his assumptions. But
other ראשונים, Rishonim, in particular רמב"ם, Rambam, that's a big ראשון, Rishon,
and the תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid say no, that's a big difference.
דברים שבלב אינם דברים devarim shebelev einam devarim is primarily a principle
by a מכר, mecher 'cause Michael's giving me money and I'm giving
him something, any condition has to be made explicit. Something going on
in my head that he doesn't have access to, it's not fair
that that would frame the terms of the transaction, right? It's only
if it's a two-sided transaction it has to be made explicit to
be part of that transaction. But if I'm giving a gift, that's
a one-sided transaction. The other side is just receiving. They're not giving
me anything, you know, it's all my act. So because it's all
my act, my subjective frame of mind can be more relevant than
in a case of a sale where it requires something more objective.
The language of the
רמב"ם Rambam is לעולם אומדין דעת הנותן. le'olam omdin da'at hanoten. You
always try to assess דעת הנותן. da'at hanoten. What was in the
subjective mindset, you know, the mindset of the one who is giving
the gift. So on the one hand, if I give a gift,
then we're going to interpret it in generous terms for the receiver
and they'll get a lot. But on the other hand, I can
say you know, there are many circumstances that I would not be
able to say in a case of a מכר mecher. like "Oh,
I never meant in this circumstance, it was not my intent to
give in this circumstance," and the whole gift will be voided. So
like an interesting balance, right? There are cases where actually in all
of these cases the receiver wins, like gets a bigger, you know,
it's read in a generous way. But there's also the flip side
of it being a very generous self-initiated one-sided type of a transaction
is also that there's more circumstances in which you could nullify the
gift, you know, based on the, based on circumstances that you said
"that wasn't what I was assuming."
Thinking of the other cases with the
120 barrel whatever. Let's say it would have been the other way
around. Give him my 120 barrel house, and we see it's only
a hundred. Do we think we just, you know,
Oh yeah, I don't
know, 'cause he had to mean something or do we say, Well...
Yeah, it's a good question, it's a good question. I don't 'cause
the גמרא's Gemara not clear with what the parameters of how flexible
we are. All right, now we move on to the issue of
הקדש. hekdesh. המקדיש שדהו הקדיש. hamakdish sadehu hikdish. Okay, you so if
you you give everything, so the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma feels הקדש
hekdesh is like מתנה, matanah. and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's
not like מתנה, matana? you don't normally include the other stuff, but
for some reason you get the trees. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is going to be the interesting position to figure out. אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, אע"ג דאמור רבנן, af al gav de'amur rabanan,
הקונה שני אילנות בתוך של חבירו, hakoneh shenei ilanot betoch shel chaveiro,
הרי זה לא קנה קרקע. harei zeh lo kana karka. So I
go ahead and I buy two trees in Michael's field. So I
do not get the land between them or the land around them,
I just get the trees. Okay, now, the, nevertheless he says, מכר
קרקע ושייר שני אילנות לפניו. machar karka veshayer shenei ilanot lefanav. If
I go ahead and I sell Michael my land and I keep
ownership of two trees, in those cases יש לו קרקע, yesh lo
karka, I do have land. The land now, what land? Now, what's
going to seem is the whole debate of how to read this:
רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות. Tosafot. Presumably not the land between the trees
and around the trees, that's assumed definitely not, beneath them. But the
question is how much beneath them? Does beneath them mean beneath them
to the fact that if the tree dies I can go ahead
and replant, I really own the land? That's the way the רשב"ם
says. Or I'm going to read it תוספות's Tosafot way. תוספות's Tosafot
way is that beneath them means that as long as the tree
is alive, I don't get, if the tree dies and gets uprooted
I don't get to replant. I only kept the tree, I didn't
keep the land. But the same way let's assume here this is
the land that is directly under the awning of the tree, okay,
but the same way that as long as tree is there, I
have rights to that land. Michael can't tell me, Dov, uproot your
tree, it's on my land. No, keeping ownership of the tree means
I have rights as long as the tree is there to have
it be there and to have it draw nutrients from the land.
You also can't tell me, Dov, here, cut down all these branches
because
it's over my land like that. No, ownership rights of the tree
mean I have rights to keep it there. So the same way
I have rights to keep it there, am I allowed during the
time that the tree is around to go ahead and like plant
like a vegetable garden here that's within the land that I have
rights to for the sake of the tree? Do I also have
rights for other things? Okay, if the tree dies, you can tell
me goodbye. But while the tree is alive and I have the
rights to that land, do I also have the rights in ways
that are not just use of the tree? That's the way the
רשב"ם—that's the way תוספות Tosfos explains it. We're going to go with
תוספות, Tosfos, I think it works a little better in the גמרא.
Gemara Okay, so he says
even though if I buy a tree, I don't have these additional
rights to this land, I just have the right to keep the
tree there. If I keep the tree for myself, okay, I am
going to hold on not only to the tree and the necessary
rights of the land but these other rights of the land as
well. Okay, and now that's obvious according to the חכמים. So the
חכמים basically would say מוכר בעין רעה מוכר. mocher b'ayin ra mocher.
So if I'm giving Michael the rest of the land, what I'm
holding on for myself, I'm going to hold on with a little
extra rights, okay? So he says like this,
מוכר קרקע ושייר שני אילנות לפניו יש לו קרקע. mocher karka v'shiyer
shnei llanos lifanav yesh lo karka. So that's פשיטא pshita according to
the רבנן. Rabbanan. Not necessarily a hundred percent because you're still giving
yourself extra rights, rights for the vegetable garden. But we're saying that
not only to the רבנן, Rabbanan, even for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva
דאמר מוכר בעין יפה מוכר, d'amar mocher b'ayin yafeh mocher, that I
do a generous or I should say I gave Michael all the
rights except those that I absolutely necessarily need for my tree. הני
מילי גבי בור ודות. Hani milei gabey bor v'dos. That's by the
well and the cistern. לא קמחשי בארעא. lo kamachshei b'ara. The fact
that when I go ahead and I retain
my well and I sell Michael the land, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says I don't retain access to the well. So why for
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says if I keep the well I
don't retain access should we say that when I keep the tree
I do retain rights to this plot? I mean if you ask
me, the access to the well is more necessary than the use
of this plot for a vegetable garden. So for רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva when I keep the well I don't keep the access, why
do when I keep the tree do I keep the rights of
this usage? So here's the reason. Because the presence of my well
in Michael's land does not damage Michael's land. There's no injury to
Michael's land. It's not drawing on it in any way and so
on.
Maybe the structure in the land kind of weakens it?
Maybe, but it's already there. Not in any ongoing way right now.
So therefore because it's not in a way necessary for me to
retain anything in Michael's land because I'm not hurting him or whatever,
I can give him the whole land, keep the well, I have
no access and he has no complaint against me that my well
is there. My well isn't doing anything to hurt him. So therefore
I give him everything and I give up my access to the
well. Okay, אבל אילנות דקמחשי בארעא. aval llanos d'kamachshei b'ara. In this
case my tree is drawing the nutrients from the land. And since
it's drawing the nutrients from the land, even when I give everything
to Michael, he might say Dov, your tree is drawing the nutrients
from the land, like uproot your tree. So I by necessity have
to maintain ownership not just of the tree but I have to
maintain rights for the tree to continue to draw the nutrients from
the land. So by necessity I'm already retaining some rights in the
land to begin with. Right? Not all rights for the vegetable garden,
but I'm retaining the right for the tree to keep on growing
there. אם איתא דלא שייר, Im issa d'lo shiyer, if I retain
no rights in this land when I kept the
tree, לימא ליה עקור אילנך וזיל. leima leh akur ilanch v'kozil. Michael
would tell me Dov, you own the tree but you cannot keep
on having it suck up my nutrients. Go rip out your tree.
So by necessity when I retain the tree I retain the rights
for it to continue to draw on the land. I get some
rights in the land. So once I get some rights in the
land I'm going to therefore that, even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who
says בעין יפה, in this case when I'm already getting some rights,
we're—רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say well then we'll give you a
little bit—we'll make those rights a little fuller. We'll say the same
rights that you have to draw the nutrients for your tree, once
you're getting rights in the land you'll also have rights to the
vegetable garden.
Yes. Yes, that you remember thirty דפים dappim ago is already impressive.
Yes.
Is that how if you have a tree on the other side
of a wall and its roots go all the way?
Right, right, how far do the roots go and so on? Yeah,
so תוספות Tosfos asks that question like he says... his question was
that wasn't—aren't we afraid that those things go much further than and
whatever? So תוספות... Tosfos... Tosafot like deals with that. Tosafot says that
maybe we're talking, I mean not exactly like that, but Tosafot says
that's why he drew the case of this of this like broad
foliage, because Tosafot says like we could be talking about a case
where even with the roots or whatever, it's still under the area
that's like under the tree itself. What?
Nutrients?
We're talking about nutrients here.
Oh, nutrients, yeah, the nutrients from the ground,
not by the...
yeah, so תוספות Tosafot tries to work out that question, that apparently
the יש לו קרקע yesh lo karka here means the קרקע karka
under the tree, and he says how does that work with the
sense that the nutrients that are grown might be much sort of
further than it? So he tries to sort of say well, we'd
be talking maybe in a case where they sort of overlapped, but
it's a good question.
וליכא צמצום. v'leika tzimtzum. Right, right. Vicky had a question?
What's the בור bor and do we use בור bor and באר
be'er interchangeably?
Yeah, so we've discussed that before. One of them, בור bor is
with a... well, I don't know, I might be using the wrong
English words, but the גמרא Gemara says that the בור bor is
a straight well dug straight into the ground and a דות dut
is with a... that you built had to build a wall inside
of the well in order to in order to retain the... because
the dirt isn't strong enough. So the ground isn't strong enough so
you need to like it's a structure built inside in order to
keep it from you know. How's it different from a באר? be'er?
I mean בור bor and באר be'er are not the same.
I know. בור bor is for like more like that it
just
collects
rainwater whereas a באר be'er hits into underground right right spring, yeah,
yeah, but yeah, we have not dealt explicitly with a באר. be'er.
I don't know sometime though I think that we are dealing with
a בור bor, that is a באר, be'er, but you're right, I
mean they are different. Most of
the... tell you an interesting thing, there was a position in the
גאונים, Ge'onim, you know the תורה Torah never says by a זב,
zav, it says a זב zav is טובל במים חיים. tovel b'mayim
chayim. But a זבה zava it never says. And what would be...
well I don't know, but it's a big נפקא מינה nafka mina
because since nowadays we treat all there's this conflation of נדה niddah
and זבה, zava, if there's an assumption that a זבה zava needs
מים חיים, mayim chayim, we couldn't use any of our מקוואות mikvaot
that are rainwater, you'd have to go go to like natural water.
And so that's why it's like you know very, very strongly the
ראשונים Rishonim say that no, no, no, a זבה's zava also good
enough for a for a normal מקוה, mikveh, you don't need מים
חיים. mayim chayim. But there's a position in the גאונים Ge'onim that
a מקוה mikveh needed a מים חיים. mayim chayim. So I'm so
like I'm like trying to figure out like how the heck did
they ever go to the מקוה. mikveh. And it's because in my
mind מים חיים mayim chayim I always think about this like wellspring
like this water like you know a spring coming up from above
the ground. But מים חיים mayim chayim also includes a באר be'er
that you dig straight down and you hit underneath water. That's מים
חיים mayim chayim because that's getting it directly from the source. And
if you go in you know in like these places in like
Europe and you know you see that a lot of ancient מקוואות
mikvaot were like they like you know talk about you know you
know like you know where our grandmothers used to go. They didn't
go a hundred miles in the snow to get to a מקוה,
mikveh, they went like a hundred feet down in a straight באר,
be'er, I'm serious, that's what they used to use for מקוואות. mikvaot.
So you know so that באר be'er what's in my mind it's
always been like a בור, but you're right, that's a באר be'er
and that's מים חיים. mayim chayim. So that you know but anyway
but yeah I don't think we're distinguishing here. Access/ability? What?
Yeah, I was thinking the same thing you know, week of disabilities?
I was really thinking what did they do all those hundreds of
years when the only way to go down into a מקוה mikveh
was they literally went I mean not a hundred feet but yes
thirty feet below straight down into get yes סכנת נפשות, sakanat nefashot,
you would think anyway. Steps presumably?
Yeah,
they had ladders or something, yeah.
So if this affords you if if already this affords you also
access to the vegetable garden, yes, does it afford you egress?
No, so that's true, easement or whatever, that seems to be not
that's still the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, and the חכמים.
Because but here the point is you don't need it's not by
necessity that I already am doing something to this part of the
field. But since already the keeping the ownership of the tree requires
for me to have real ownership of the tree that I have
rights to draw on the nutrients, so then we're saying well then
even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would agree that you have other rights
as well. That's the argument. Okay, תנן, tenan, now we're going to
see if we can sort of defend this or not. רבי שמעון
אומר המקדיש את השדה לא הקדיש אלא חרוב המורכב וסדן השקמה. Rabbi
Shimon omer hamakdish et hasadeh lo hikdish ela charuv hamurkav v'saddan hashikma.
Okay, so this is this weird idea that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says, I'm not going to treat הקדש hektesh like a מתנה. matana?
If you're מקדיש makdish your field you keep the other components of
the field,
but the things you don't keep are these trees. Now why are
those trees different? ותניא עלה אמר רבי שמעון, v'tanya alah amar Rabbi
Shimon, so good we have a ברייתא braita where רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon explains himself. מה טעם, ma ta'am, what's the reason I say
this? הואיל ויונקים משדה הקדש, ho'il v'yonkim misedey hektesh, because they they
draw on the nutrients of the הקדש hektesh field. So here we
go, I was מקדיש... makdish... I was מקדיש makdish *makdish* this field.
Now, assuming that I kept the ownership of this tree to myself.
Okay, now.
I was מקדיש *makdish* this field. Assuming I kept the ownership of
this tree to myself, my tree would now be drawing, getting nutrients
from הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*’s field. And I would be over on a
מעילה *me’ilah*. Okay, because I would now be benefiting from הקדש hekdesh
*hekdesh*’s field. So one way of saying this is, in order that
I shouldn’t be being over on מעילה *me’ilah*, I obviously was מקדיש
*makdish* the trees as well. I didn’t want to keep trees in
a הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* field.
The other way
the רשב"ם *Rashbam* says it, although this doesn’t work as well I
think, is that since it is drawing from the הקדש *hekdesh* field,
then the principle is that it’s גידולים *gidulim* of הקדש *hekdesh*. It’s
stuff that grows from הקדש *hekdesh* and belongs to הקדש *hekdesh*. But
the problem is that the
tree, meaning maybe any extra growth of the tree would belong to
הקדש *hekdesh*. That would be stuff that grew from הקדש *hekdesh*’s field,
but the main tree existed prior. So I think one way of
understanding it is, in order that I shouldn’t be עובר *over* on
drawing, having my tree benefit, I’m packaging the whole thing. Okay, but
because the field is הקדש *hekdesh* and the tree is growing and
draws from the field, I’m being מקדיש *makdish* the tree as well.
That’s his principle. That’s why I really want to assume that you’re
not generous with הקדש *hekdesh*, but the tree has to be included
because the tree is growing from הקדש *hekdesh*’s field. Yes.
I don’t see that in the language yet. המקדיש את השדה *Hamakdish
et hasadeh*, I’m going to be מקדיש *makdish* my field. When I
do
that, לא הקדיש אלא חרוב
המורכב
וסדן השקמה *lo hikdish ela charuv hamurkav
vesadan hashekma*.
No, not on the land, no, not on all that extra, other
extra stuff.
Yeah, because it was in contrast to the line before which says
המקדיש את השדה הקדיש את כולה *Hamakdish et hasadeh hikdish et kullah*.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר *Rabbi Shimon omer*, מקדיש *makdish* לא הקדיש
אלא חרוב המורכב *lo hikdish ela hacharuv hamurkav*. I mean I guess
you could read it not even the field itself, which would be
a pretty bizarre read. Okay, but it’s read in contrast to כולה
*kullah*. That we’re talking about the stuff that’s not the field itself.
You said everything in the field, no. The only thing in the
field that you get that’s not the field itself is the חרוב
השקמה *charuv hashikma*. You have to I understand what you’re saying, but
you have to read it in contrast to the previous line. And
it clearly doesn’t work here in the explanation of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, right? הואיל ויונקים משדי הקדש *Ho’il veyonkim misday hekdesh*. That only
makes sense if you’re also מקדיש *makdish* the field itself. הואיל ויונקים
משדי הקדש *Ho’il veyonkim misday hekdesh*. Yeah. Okay, all right, so let’s
see now what the גמרא *Gemara* does with it. Okay, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this, ואי סלקא דעתך כחיה שייר *ve’isalka da’atach
k’chaya shayer*, so the גמרא *Gemara* is saying but I don’t get
it, says the גמרא *Gemara*. If רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*
is saying fundamentally this is
like מכר *mecher*, okay, fundamentally this is like מכר *mecher*, but I
have to say that I gave the חרוב *charuv* because otherwise it’ll
be יונק yonek, משדי הקדש *yonek misday hekdesh*. He says but it
wouldn’t be יונק yonek משדי הקדש *yonek misday hekdesh*. This is a
classic example that you are selling the field, retaining the ownership of
the tree for yourself, right? And what do you get when you
retain ownership of the tree for yourself? You get the right to
be יונק *yonek*. You retain those rights. Okay, maybe
it’s not all yours, but at least you get the right that
it should be יונק *yonek* from it. Okay, so therefore why do
you have to say that the tree got sold with it? It’s
a classic example, you retain the tree and it retains for you
the rights of that land. Okay, so obviously you see according to
this he thinks that even when you retain a tree for
yourself you don’t retain those rights.
So the גמרא *Gemara* is saying רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* fine, says
the גמרא *Gemara*, רבי שמעון דאמר כרבי עקיבא *Rabbi Shimon d’amar k’Rabbi
Akiva*. Take back what we said before. Before we said רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva* would concede the point that you would get
these rights even though he says בעין יפה מוכר *be’ayin yafah mocher*,
here he would concede the point that you get these rights. Now
we’re saying otherwise. Now we’re saying that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva* would say that when you sell the land you do not
have the right to the space under the tree. בעין יפה מוכר
*be’ayin yafah mocher*. And therefore רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* working within רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva*. Now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
would say if you’re מקדיש *makdish* it’s בעין יפה מקדיש *be’ayin yafah
makdish* and you give it all. So רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* is
like a hybrid, right? רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* basically is saying, number
one, like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, בעין יפה מוכר *be’ayin
yafah mocher*. But unlike רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* he is saying that
הקדש *hekdesh* is like מכר *mecher*. Okay, so it’s בעין יפה *be’ayin
yafah* but it’s still like מכר *mecher*. So it’s not that you
get everything. So you’re מקדיש *makdish* the field, you retain ownership over
the well and over the chicken coop and the whole thing. We
don’t say that הקדש *hekdesh* is like מתנה matana. *matanah*, הקדש *hekdesh*
is like מכר *mecher*. Okay, but the thing that you do sell,
the field itself, that’s בעין יפה *be’ayin yafah*. And since the field
so this is not the field itself and therefore these things don’t
go along, but the stuff... is the field is עין יפה. So
therefore, not only are you selling, you're even selling the field directly
under the tree, right? That's רבי עקיבא עין יפה, Rabbi Akiva ayin
yafe, and once you're selling the field under the tree and you're
not retaining any rights to it, well now you have a tree
growing from a field of הקדש, so now you're going to have
to be giving this tree as הקדש as well.
All right, so I understand conceptually you work it out that way
on the model of מכירה, mechira, yeah, but why would you, but
but isn't it just so obvious that הקדש is an example of
a gift to the המקדש? Hamikdash?
Yeah, I understand. I mean, yeah, I mean that's obviously the other
position. Yeah, I don't know, why did like why does he treat
this different as a מתנה? Experientially. Right, right, experientially.
That's my question. When I'm מקדיש my field, how is it I'm
experiencing
different than a מתנה?
What am I getting?
Yeah, I don't know. It's a good question. Like why he treats
this different as a מתנה.
Like I'm getting something theologically, metaphysically, like, you know.
Right, right, right, right. I'm getting זכות. zechut. I guess, because God
was good to me, I only said I was going to give
this, that was my deal with God, it was still a מכר.
That's like, okay, anyway. But the thing is, the thing is that
before we said that even according to רבי עקיבא pro-עין יפה, Rabbi
Akiva ayin yafe, you still retain the right, and now we're saying
no, for רבי עקיבא עין יפה, the same way you don't retain
access to your well, you don't retain the rights to the land
under your tree. And once you don't retain the rights to your
land under your tree and you don't and you then you are
with then you are without any rights drawing on the שדה הקדש,
sdeh hekdesh, so therefore you have to give the tree as well.
That's the way רבי שמעון says. Now of course the question is
according to this, so does that mean according to רבי עקיבא, I
sell you my land, I retain my tree, I don't retain the
rights to be יונק, so you can tell me at any time,
rip up your tree? It sounds like maybe the answer is yes.
You know, I'm I know it wouldn't make sense, but but I'm
thinking, yeah,
it's sort of like Lowe's and you buy a tree, there's no
assumption that you're like
buying it with the land where it's played right, take the tree.
I understand, like if I've got a tree growing my land I
think the tree. Anyway, I'm just saying now that the גמרא is
saying that at least according that according to רבי עקיבא you don't
have rights, does it mean I just don't have rights for the
vegetable garden? That's what we were talking about before. Does it mean
I don't have really any rights at all and you can tell
me to uproot it? All right, but anyway, so now we've had
to modify and say what we said before was not true according
to רבי עקיבא. רבי עקיבא would say you do not retain those
rights. So let's just read one more line. Okay, רב הונא Rav
Huna says like the רבנן Rabbanan and רב הונא Rav Huna that
says that you have those rights, so he's going back like the
רבנן Rabbanan and therefore בעין רעה מוכר, be'ayin ra'a mocher, and therefore
you have rights under the tree. So the גמרא says כרבנן פשיטא.
kerabbanan peshita. Of course! According to רבנן Rabbanan you're בעין רעה מוכר.
be'ayin ra'a mocher. You'd have access to your well, so you have
rights for your tree to grow from the land. So the גמרא
says no, נפקא מינא דנפלה הדר שתיל להו. nafka mina denafala hadar
shatil lehu.
It's not so פשיטא. peshita. Because now the way תוספות Tosafot reads,
now we're saying something we didn't say before. It might have been
פשיטא peshita that if I keep my well I have access to
my well, if I keep my tree my tree has rights to
be יונק from the land, maybe it's even a פשיטא peshita that
I have rights to use that land, but now we're going to
have in order that רב הונא Rav Huna should be saying a
חידוש, chiddush we're going to say further: that if the tree actually
gets uprooted, I really own the land. I have a right to
replant. Okay, maybe maybe I don't fully own the land, okay, but
at least I have a right to have a tree on an
ongoing in perpetuity in that place.
So you can't then put
like a house on it. Exactly, maybe I can't build a house
on it, but the rights that I retain for myself for the
רבנן Rabbanan are serious rights. So רב הונא'ס Rav Huna's claim was
when I retain a tree for myself, I retain rights to the
land. The first version was this is even according to רבי עקיבא.
Since for רבי עקיבא you need to have the tree there, it
needs to have rights to grow, that gives you more rights. Then
we seem to say, oh, based on this רבי שמעון, it sounds
like at least רבי עקיבא would say you don't retain rights. So
if we're only saying according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, what's the חידוש?
And the חידוש is that you retain like serious rights, not just
as long as the tree is there, but even to replant a
tree. Okay, so we will I guess we'll end here because we're
already one דף out and shouldn't get even further, so we will
pick up with this tomorrow. Okay.